<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse on the extensiveness and comprehensiveness of future judgment of God In another method than what hath been hitherto extant in any other books or sermons upon this subject. By Richard Stafford.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5115A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895993</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2372:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse on the extensiveness and comprehensiveness of future judgment of God In another method than what hath been hitherto extant in any other books or sermons upon this subject. By Richard Stafford.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgment of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153617:1"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE ON THE Extenſiveneſs and Comprehenſiveneſs OF THE Future Judgment of God, In another Method than what hath been hitherto Extant in any other BOOKS or SERMONS upon this Subject.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>AS to the extenſiveneſs of the <hi>future Judgment of God,</hi> That is, How far it will reach back, even to all the days of this Life, after we are come unto the knowledge of Good and Evil unto the day of ones Death; and as to the comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs thereof, How much it will take in, even all the Deeds here done in the Body, I ground all this on the following Scriptures. And here the firſt ſort of Scriptures which I ſhall make uſe of, are but conjectural to illuſtrate this Truth; and the others ſhall be ſo plain and expreſs even to confirm and demonſtrate it. An inſtance of the firſt ſort of Scriptures may be like that <hi>Viſion which Paul had ſeen of one ſaying, Come over into</hi> Macedonia, <hi>and help us. And immediately we endeavoured to go into</hi> Macedonia, <hi>aſſuredly gathering that the Lord had called us for to preach the Goſpel unto them.</hi> Acts 16.10. and ſo that place in <hi>Acts</hi> 13.34. <hi>As concerning that he raiſed him from the dead
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153617:2"/>now no more to turn into corruption: He ſaid on this wiſe, I will give you the ſure Mercies of David.</hi> And ſo our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt proves the Reſurrection of the Dead from that ſaying, <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob. God is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living.</hi> Mat. 22.32. For there is a way by aſſuredly gathering and reaſoning out of the Scriptures to bring out ſuch and ſuch Truths, altho' they ſeem to ſpeak nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in plain and expreſs Words, as it was here in the matter of the Reſurrection. And ſo it may ſeem odd and unuſual at firſt (until the Reader comes to know the Reaſon thereof) if I ſhould ground the extenſiveneſs of the future Judgment from Deut. 1.39. <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over your little ones which you ſaid ſhould be a Prey, and your Children which in that day had no knowledg: between good and evil, they ſhall go in thither, and unto them will I give it, and they ſhall poſſeſs it.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intimating, That thoſe Little ones and Children, becauſe they had not the knowledge of Good and Evil, therefore they ſhould be freed and exempted from that Puniſhment which was to befall their Fathers of their Carcaſſes falling in the Wilderneſs. But the Little ones and Children for the aforeſaid Reaſon <hi>(Becauſe in that day they had no knowledge between good and evil)</hi> Therefore they ſhould go in and poſſeſs that good Land. So that if they were to avoid a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and inherit a Bleſſing; becauſe by their not having the knowledge of Good and Evil, they had done nothing worthy of a forfeiture and loſs of that Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>It may be again reaſoned on the other hand, That Children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed have not the knowledge of Good and Evil. And it is elſewhere written, <hi>And the Times of this Ignorance God winked at.</hi> Acts 17.29. ſo it may be ſuppoſed for the ſame Reaſon, That God <hi>winks</hi> at the Sins and Follies of that tender Age. But as for Boys and Girls when they come to have the knowledge of Good and Evil, then they are accountable before God, and ſo likewiſe are thoſe of Youth and riper Years. But much more are they accountable that are of full knowledge, even thoſe who by Reaſon of uſe have their Senſes exerciſed to diſcern both Good and Evil. As people come to know good and evil, and to diſcern between good and evil, ſo they are accountable and muſt be judged, and receive accordingly. To the Good is annexed Reward, and to the Evil, Puniſhment, ſo is the very order and eſtabliſhment of the things of God. And ſo indeed it is from the Reaſon of Things. As indeed all the things of the All-wiſe God, who is wonderful in Counſel and excellent in Working, are ordained and eſtabliſhed with very Great reaſon; as it will appear yet more evidently to us than any knowledge of Man can now bring forth, when He <hi>himſelf will ſpeak and teſtifie.</hi> Pſal. 50.7. And <hi>He will gather all Nations</hi> (under which is comprehended of all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) <hi>into the Valley of Jehoſaphat, and will plead with them</hi> there.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153617:2"/>
               <hi>Joel.</hi> 3.2. for what they have done on this Earth. It is certain that God doth more regard the Iniquities of Youth than of Childhood, upon this very ſame Reaſon. For Children have no knowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil, but Youth hath, or may have, which is the ſame thing which by the way doth anſwer that common Deceit of People, as if Ignorance would excuſe their Sin and Ungodlineſs, which it will in no wiſe, but rather increaſe and aggravate their Sin; for their <hi>Ignorance was willing.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.5. and wilful. God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that when we know his Will, we ſhould do it; otherwiſe we ſin and are liable to his Indignation. And alſo the ſame God doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that Boys and Girls, Young men, and Maidens, ſhould learn and receive the Knowledge of his Will before, or however as ſoon as they come to know any other thing; and as ſoon as ever the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Reaſon are widened or employed about other things, they ſhould be uſed towards God, and for the apprehending the things of his Kingdom. In the ſame Scriptures whereby we muſt be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and according to which we muſt receive according to our works we do not find any of the Saints and Servants of the Lord complaining of the ſins and vanities of Childhood, nor yet praying for Pardon and Forgiveneſs of the ſame. But by that Expreſſion of <hi>Paul, When I was a Child, I ſpake as a Child, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as a child, I thought as a child;</hi> It is imported as if God would paſs all that over, and not enter into judgment for the ſame. But it is not ſo as to Youth, for we read otherwiſe concerning that; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the ſins of my Youth, nor my Tranſgreſſions.</hi> Pſal. 25.7. The <hi>Pſalmist</hi> here knew by the Spirit that without his deprecating and praying againſt them, God would remember them, and call him to an account for the ſame. For ſo his ſervant <hi>Job</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>Thou writeſt bitter things against me, and makeſt me to poſſeſs the Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my Youth.</hi> Job 13.26. And ſo his own Spirit ſaith by the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah, Surely after that I was turned. I repented, and after I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh: I was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>d, yea even confounded, becauſe I did bear the reproach of my Youth.</hi> Jer. 31.19. The juſt Judge of all the Earth calls to account for thoſe Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions committed in Youth, all one as of ſucce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding years. As in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in ſome time about Youth is that <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct Day</hi> (God only knows it) from which Day forward to the Day of each perſon's Death, God doth commence and begin the time from which he will call to account for all the following days of Life: Like as whether it be in Manhood, declining years or old Age, God only knows when it is. He <hi>limiteth a certain Day, ſaying in David, To day after ſo long a time.</hi> Heb. 4.7. after which if they will come to repentance they will be hardly admitted. So in the foregoing part of Life, there is a <hi>certain Day,</hi> from which Day forward, God will call in queſtion and to account, and ſo of every day, after we are come to the years of Diſcretion, and have the knowledge of Good and Evil.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153617:3"/>
            <p>And this I ſhall not ſo much ground upon as aſſuredly gather from another conjectural Scripture, as I phraſe it, which is the concluding part of the Speech of the Town-Clerk of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> for <hi>we are in danger to be called in queſtion for this days <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oroar, there being no Cauſe whereby we may give an account of this days Conoourſe.</hi> Acts 19.40. So in like manner I alledge and reaſon, That we are not ſo much in danger (which denotes Doubt and Uncertainty whether it would be ſo or not; and probably for all he ſpoke thus they were never called in queſtion for the ſame as we read of.) But I go on to add, That we every one of us, ſhall be certainly called in queſtion for this Day, and ſo of all the paſt Days after Years of Diſcretion, and ſo of all the following Days; for each days actions and deeds done in the Body; yea, for the Thoughts of Heart, and for the Words of our Tongue. For they muſt be given <hi>account of,</hi> according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35, 36, 37. and whether there was a Cauſe or no Cauſe for the ſame, yet of every thing we muſt give account. Many may be apt to think that this is but a ſlender foundation to build ſo great a Truth and Aſſertion upon as that here is. For the Town-Clerk of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was an Heathen, and a worſhipper of the Great Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> and he ſaid this as to a Temporal matter, and when he ſpake after this manner, he thought nothing at all of the <hi>Future judgment</hi> of God. How then canſt thou bring this Saying of his to manifeſt a great Truth of God, as to declare his Decree of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgment to be on that wiſe, as thou haſt here affirmed it: Why therefore miſtake me not, I do only allude to thoſe his words but. I do in no wiſe bring them for proof and confirmation of this Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the extenſiveneſs and comprehenſiveneſs of the <hi>future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> For indeed they are no proof at all, or at leaſt a very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one. Only from the parity and likeneſs of the Proceedings in Humane Courts of Judicatory, with thoſe of the laſt and great Day of the Lord, in which indeed there is ſome ſimilitude. For the Great Judge of all the Earth will proceed againſt all Mankind with the ſame meaſures of Juſtice as they now do one to another; for he gave them knowledge thus to proceed and judge. And from the ſame Reaſoning. <hi>Shall not he that teacheth man knowledge know?</hi> It may be certainly concluded, for he often makes ſuch compariſons and reſemblances, that he will ſo deal with us Creatures in <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, juſtice</hi> and <hi>equity. Pſal.</hi> 98.9. as is now commonly uſed in Courts of Judicatory, when they proceed according to the true and exact Rules thereof. But ſimilitudes do illuſtrate and not prove. But here we have no need thereof, for let alone that Saying of the Town-clerk of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which I only mentioned becauſe his words did ſo appoſitely expreſs forth our Subject in hand, and ſo plainly that it may be underſtood by the meaneſt capacity: We have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſundry expreſs, plain and full places of undoubted Scripture,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153617:3"/>which make known the comprehenſiveneſs and extenſiveneſs of the future Judgment, as hath been afore-affirmed. As alſo herein dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the future Judgment of God from Human Aſſizes or Seſſions, or Common Courts of Judgment. For many things are here done on this Earth, whereof no notice or cognizance at all is taken at Aſſizes, Seſſions, Court-leets, or ſuch like. And then alſo they do only take notice of ſome Misfeſances, Nuſances, Evil, Prejudice or Harms, either as to the Society of Mankind, or as relating to Property, which many times through Bribery, Corruption, Partiality, or the Greatneſs of the Perſon do paſs uncenſured without Animadverſion or Puniſhment. And then they do not reward thoſe that do well, or who keep up the good and peace of Community. Now herein the Judgment of the Great God ſupplies what is wanting or defective as to that. <hi>He is a Great God, mighty and terrible, that regardeth not perſons, nor taketh Reward,</hi> in all which he is oppoſite unto Men. And then as his Providence doth reach over Sparrows, for not one of them falleth to the ground without the Will of our Heavenly Father, as the Hairs of our Head are all numbred, and not one of them is forgotten before God. As his <hi>eyes are upon all the ways of the ſons of Men</hi> (Mark that particle, all) To give every one <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his way, and according to the fruit of his doings.</hi> Jer. 32.19. So he will bring them all to Judgment; for not one thing whether it be great or ſmall, of more or leſs moment, whether the greateſt King, or meaneſt Beggar had an hand in it <hi>(For not only the Kings of the Earth, and the Great Men, and the Rich Men, and the Chief Captains, and the Mighty Men, but every Bond man will alſo come forth unto Judgment)</hi> I ſay again, not any thing that was ever done or tranſacted on this Earth from the Cedar in Lebanon to the Hyſſop on the Wall, but will come forth into Judgment. <hi>For God will bring every work into judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be bad.</hi> Eccleſ. 12.14. Here is a moſt plain and expreſs Text, which proves and confirms the point in hand, of the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs and comprehenſiveneſs of the future Judgment, beſides that ſaying of the Town-clerk of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which barely as it comes from him is not to be relied on. But this of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> is a moſt certain Truth, and proceeds from the Spirit of God. <hi>Every work, and every ſecret thing.</hi> There is ſome of this ſort done and Tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every day, and night after night, ſo that each days tranſactions and ſecret things, yea and every leaſt thing ſhall be brought into Judgment, whether it be good or whether it be evil. This makes out again what is afore-affirmed, for the Judgment of Man in Courts of Judicatory doth chiefly and almoſt only take notice of the Evil. But God will bring both the Good and the Evil into judgment. And that God will judge for all the actions of Youth; as to which many think that they ſhall eſcape ſcotfree and unpuniſhed; we have this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153617:4"/>expreſly averr'd and affirmed in the foregoing Chapter, <hi>Rejoyce, O young man in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the light of thine eyes; but know thou that for all theſe things, God will bring thee into judgment.</hi> Eccleſ. 11.9. Obſerve here again this laſt: For all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment. And ſome of all theſe things are done every day by the young Man: So that the conſequence is evident, that of every day after we are come to the knowledge of Good and Evil, we ſhall certainly be called in queſtion, yea and be called to the Bar of God, for to give an account for the ſame. Many think of what is paſt as if it were over and there is no more to be ſaid thereof. It ſeems forgotten and periſhed, and to be come to an utter end. But the word ſaith otherwiſe, <hi>God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that which is paſt.</hi> Eccl. 3.15. yea all one as the preſent; for what is paſt, was once preſent alſo; and what is now preſent will ſoon be paſt. The judgment of God will be retrograde, or by way of rehearſal, or remembring, or ripping up of former miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, as we commonly ſay, or by reciting up the ſeveral Thoughts, Words and Actions of this Life that now is. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done and I kept ſilence: thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf, but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in order before thine eyes.</hi> Pſal. 50.21. That is, in order and ſucceſſion of time, as each thing was done and committed, together with the other circumſtances of place and manner, and ſuch like, as alſo with the ſeveral aggravations belonging thereunto, ſome inſtances whereof are given in this ſame Fiftieth <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and many more there are throughout the Book of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Another great Scripture which proves the extenſiveneſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſiveneſs of the future Judgment, as before explained, is, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Christ, that every one may receive the Things done in his Body, according to that he hath done whether it be good or bad.</hi> It is ſaid Deeds, indefinitely which reaches to all the deeds done in the Body. Like as when it is ſaid in general words, <hi>It is appointed unto men once to die;</hi> That is, It is ſo appointed unto all men once to die, as we ſenſibly know: And truly, even common Reaſon manifeſteth the very ſame; for if we were to receive for ſome Deeds done in the Body, Why not for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deeds as well as for them, and ſo on till it comes to all; as indeed the Decree of God and our caſe is, <hi>The Lord looketh upon all the Inhabitants of the Earth, he conſidereth all their Works.</hi> Pſal. 33.14.15. <hi>And give to every man according to his way whoſe heart thou knoweſt; for thou, even thou only knoweſt the hearts of all the Children of Men.</hi> 1 Kings 8.39. And ſo all thoſe other places of Scripture, as there are many, which ſpeak of Gods rewarding or rendring unto the Children of Men, according to their works, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153617:4"/>to their deeds and ſuch like; all theſe do manifeſt and make known the comprehenſiveneſs and extenſiveneſs of the future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo all theſe Deeds done in the Body, the ſeveral works and ways are done in the ſeveral days of our Life, ſome in one day, and ſome in another; ſo that the ſame Truth holds firm that of this day, and of all the paſt days, and of all the ſucceeding days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this time of my publiſhing this unto ye, and the day of our ſeveral reſpective Deaths, we ſhall be called to an account. We muſt give account of this Concourſe (whereof I hope we ſhall give a good one with joy and comfort; our only end and deſign herein being to worſhip the God of Heaven and Earth, and to hear his word.) I muſt give account of every Sermon that I preach or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, that I be faithful in the handling thereof, not ſhunning to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto ye the whole Counſel of God, and to make known the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth, whether it pleaſes or diſpleaſes Man <hi>(for if I yet pleaſed Men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Christ.)</hi> Through good and evil Report, as Deceivers, and yet true. And ye muſt give account of your Hearing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye do mind and are attentive unto the ſame, and how ye profit and edifie thereby. How ye ponder and remember it in your hearts. But chiefly that ye <hi>continue therein.</hi> Good God! how much doſt thou delight in this one thing of continuing? <hi>The Children of thy Servants ſhall continue.</hi> Pſal. 102.28. <hi>But whoſo looketh into the perfect Law of Liberty and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful Hearer, but a doer of the Word, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deeds.</hi> James 1.25. This is the principal Matter to be doers of the Word and not Hearers only. Though ye are to be Hearers alſo before ye can be doers. For a man cannot do a thing before he knows it. God will likewiſe call the Non-hearers of his Word to an account for the ſame, for their diſobedience and rebellion, for their ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and perverſeneſs therein, which is the ſame as if a Son or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſhould be obſtinately reſolved not to Hear what his Father or Maſter will ſay unto him. All thoſe Threatnings and evil Things, as they are many which are written and ſpoken forth in the Book of the Lord againſt ſuch who refuſe to hear his words, will be fulfilled upon them unto their greater Condemnation. So it will be of the ſeveral Seaſons and Opportunities of Prayer, whether it be private Prayer in ones Cloſet, or Family-Prayer, or Prayer in the Cougre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Aſſemblies of his People, of all this we muſt give an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as alſo of all our other holy Things, and of all acts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever pertaining to Religion; and ſo likewiſe of all the doings of common Life, otherwiſe than what are meerly natural and neceſſary, and ſo of all the Tranſactions between Man and man. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done by any Men or Women under the Sun in any Country or Language of the Earth, whether the ſame be done by Nations, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153617:5"/>or ſingle Perſons in any Time or Generation, but what will come into account and examination, and to be heard and decided over again at the Judgement of the Great God. Indeed there will be <hi>multitudes, multitudes in the Valley of Deciſion.</hi> Joel 3.14. So that what appearance is ever at the greateſt Aſſizes, or at the Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous of the moſt numerous Armies, or the greateſt. Concourſe of People to ſee ſome extraordinary ſight in populous Cities; all this will be no more to the multitude and number of Creatures which ſhall be then gathered together in the great Day of God, then a ſingle Man is now in compariſon of an hundred thouſand or a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. I have heard to this purpoſe that the Schoolmen ſhould ſay, That becauſe of the multiplicity of Buſineſs, and the multitude of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which ſhall appear then, thereupon they ſuppoſe that the Day of Judgment will laſt a thouſand years. But herein they imagine and talk after the manner of Men: <hi>For known unto God are all his works from the Beginning of the World,</hi> as alſo the Times and Seaſons which the Father hath kept in his own Power, or rather that will be the Inhabitation of Eternity, where is no ſuch thing as the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering or reckoning of Times and Seaſons. So that they had better let alone ſuch kind of Imaginations as to what time it ſhall laſt; But rather <hi>purifie our hearts by Faith,</hi> by believing and always bearing in Mind that theſe things ſhall certainly be in the General, although we know no more as to the exact Method of procedure, How that God and Chriſt will make that Great, Final and Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deciſion between the Righteous and the Wicked, between thoſe who ſerve God and obey the Goſpel, and who did not; As to the Particulars hereof, nor to what exact method of Duration all this ſhall laſt (for time will then be no longer) than Brute Beaſts do now know thoſe Rules by which Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice, But we are to be as wiſe Stewards, to caſt up and prepare our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts beforehand, and to do nothing but what our Lord will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and like of. Such as was in the way of Service and Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not what will be found fault withal, or blamed by him. So much ſin or evil as hath been committed, <hi>This ſhall be a witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; It is an heaping up Treaſure together for the laſt days.</hi> Jam. 5.3. <hi>It is a treaſuring up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi> Rom. 2.5. And though already <hi>the Pile thereof is fire and much wood.</hi> Iſa. 30.33. which is ordained for the puniſhment of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels and condemned Sinners. Yet here again the more Sin and Tranſgreſſion which they have committed is an adding more Fuel to that Fire, which ſhall torment but not conſume them. So on the other and better hand, the <hi>doing good works is a laying in a foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal Life;</hi> theſe works follow them: So that to do good works is a ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to ones ſelf true and ſolid Comfort in a Dying-day, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153617:5"/>reaches and extends it ſelf throughout all Eternity. Beſides that, it is ſweet and ſenſible in the greateſt time of need: So that it will be certainly better for each Man or Woman the more Obedience and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Godlineſs, and Good he hath done throughout his foregoing Life.</p>
            <p>Here is a real Argument not to continue in Sin one moment long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: for notwithſtanding the preſent pleaſure or conveniency, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he miſſes of ſo much more Happineſs and Advantage in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Recompence. Again, we ſhould not a minute longer neglect obedience and doing good; for this would be to loſe ſo much of a <hi>full Reward.</hi> 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. Thus much is ſignified from the <hi>righteous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, who will render to every one according to his deeds.</hi> Rom. 2.5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And ſo it is written, <hi>For the Son of Man ſhall come in the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Father with his holy Angels, and then he ſhall reward every man according to his works.</hi> Mat. 16.27. <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, for great is your reward in Heaven.</hi> Mat. 5.11, 12. <hi>Every man ſhall receive his own Reward according to his own Labour.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.8. <hi>Wo unto their Soul, for they have rewarded evil unto themſelves. Say to the righteous, it ſhall be well with him, for they ſhall eat the fruit of their doings. Wo unto the Wicked, it ſhall be ill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him,</hi> Iſa. 3.9, 10, 11. <hi>According to their deeds, accordingly he will repay.</hi> Iſa. 59.18. <hi>The great God that formeth all things, both rewardeth the Fool, and rewardeth Tranſgreſſors.</hi> Prov. 26.18. <hi>As thou haſt done, it ſhall be done unto thee; thy reward ſhall return upon thine own head.</hi> Obad. 1.15. <hi>Receiving in themſelves that Recompence of their Error that was meet.</hi> Rom. 1, 27. <hi>Like as the Lord of Hoſts thought to do unto us, according to our wayes, and according to our doings, ſo hath he dealt with us.</hi> Zech. 1.6. <hi>All the Churches ſhall know that I am He which ſearcheth the hearts and reins. And I will give unto every one of you according to his works.</hi> Rev. 2.23. <hi>And behold I come quickly, and my Reward is with me to give every Man according as his work ſhall be.</hi> Rev. 22.12. There are ſundry other like places of Scripture, which the more they are conſidered of and looked into, they do the more ſhew how that the future Judgment and Retribution ſhall be proportioned, and <hi>meaſured out.</hi> Mat. 7.1. and exactly adjuſted <hi>(judgment will I lay to the line and righteouſneſs to the plummet)</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Deeds of Men. As it will be yet more clearly ſeen at the revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God, It ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly diſcloſed and ſhewed unto every one, though it hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hidden from ſome, becauſe they would not ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, for there they might have found it ſo, and accordingly have prepared to have given up their Accounts. The Good may be hence Quickened to do more, to lay hold of every opportunity, to lay up for themſelves a greater foundation againſt the time to come by Good works, and ſeek and do the work of the Lord diligently, and to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153617:6"/>improve every Talent to the utmoſt. And the evil might have preſently ceaſed to do wickedly, they ſhould have turned and have been yet more zealous in the other way. Like unto <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> who loved much becauſe much had been forgiven unto her. And <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe he had been a Perſecutor, he laboured more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly than the other Apoſtles, and yet not He but the Grace of God which was in him. And ſo the ſame Inſtruction is to all, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their foregoing Life they have been ſinuers or religious, yet to labour more abundan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly for the the time to come than the reſt of his Brethren and Fellow-creatures. And ſee well to it, that he exceed them in great Seriouſneſs and Holineſs, Purity and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life.</p>
            <p>In the time of my late Adverſity and Trouble, a fond Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vain deſire did ariſe in my mind, I would fain have God do more for me than he uſually doth for other peeple in like caſes. But this ſame kind of Imagination and vain Deſire was beaten back, anſwer'd and ſatisfied again by this inward Reaſoning which at the very ſame time did ſpring up in my Heart; Why ſhould I expect that God ſhould do more for me than for other People, when I did not exceed my Brethren, and come out from among them, and get above them in the Godly and holy Life. For though I have been ſometimes in the heights, all for God and Seriouſneſs, and <hi>in the Spirit</hi> for a little time whilſt I was by my ſelf and in Retirement, and I reſolved what I would do; How that I would ſtill keep unto that Strictneſs, yet I was again like the Children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who being harneſſed and carrying Bows, turned themſelves back in the day of Battle. So though I had Grace and Preparation beforehand, to arm my ſelf withal: Yet for all that I have not ſtood but faln in the Time of Trial and Temptation; for after all thoſe Thoughts and Purpoſes aforementioned, when I have come into Company, and amongſt a mixt People, I have put on again the ſame vain and worldly Converſation. I have talked and had that which ſavours of Men; and the Grace and Spirit of the Lord hath ſenſibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from me for a time; and I have been weak and all one as another Man. I wiſh I could here tell it weeping; but it is a real grief of Soul when I throughly conſider of it. I my ſelf have a great deal to anſwer and account for before God, in that I have not at all times and in all places, and in all Companies lived according to that Grace and Knowledge which God hath given me; that at the very ſame time when I did know and approve of the things more excellent, yet I did not follow them, but rather I did the worſe. How many precious and ſeaſonable Truths have I conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and kept within, when in Duty I ought to have ſpoken them out. I ſpeak all this to my ſhame, and to my fault which ſhould be amended. But as I am declaring this unto ye, remember that your
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153617:6"/>Hearts be alſo upon the ſearch and examination, whether it hath not been ſo with ye likewiſe. And I do therefore bring forth theſe Things unto ye, becauſe that it is good to know our Faults in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to amend them. As alſo to put you in mind, ſtir up and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort ye, <hi>And let us conſider one another to provoke unto Love and good works.</hi> Heb. 10.24. As it is commonly adviſed, <hi>Be ſure to keep be beſt Company,</hi> which in the meaning of the World is the Richeſt. But this is a falſe way of ſpeaking, for they are not the beſt as may be underſtood from the word of Truth, and will be ſeen at the Judgment of the Great Day; ſo I would recommend to ye, to ſet before ye the very beſt Examples of all, the very beſt Saints and Servants of God that are in the Town or Neighbourhood wherein ye inhabit, and there try your beſt ſkill, and uſe your utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that as the other Diſciple did out-run <hi>Peter;</hi> So do thou uſe diligence, and put forth all thy ſtrength if thou canſt out-run ſuch an one in the Chriſtian-race; for if thou wouldſt not upon a falſe Imagination or vain Hopes, <hi>(which are like the Dream of one that eateth, and he awaketh and his Soul is empty,)</hi> but upon rational and aſſured grounds have God do more for thee in this World and in the World to come, as to have a <hi>Benjamin's Meſs or a double Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Spirit,</hi> or to be brought out of Trouble; for ſo is the Promiſe to the Righteous, when the Wicked are left therein, then thou muſt exceed them alſo in Godlineſs <hi>(which hath the promiſe of this Life, and of that which is to come)</hi> and in <hi>righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> It is very well worth our while to ſtrive to be utmoſt herein; becauſe that the future recompence of God will be proportioned out, and it will be infinitely ſo much beyond all the Pain, Uncouthneſs, Labour, Backwardneſs, which was ever in any Act or Inſtance of well-doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls as they that must give account.</hi> Heb. 13.17. Theſe laſt words, As <hi>they that muſt give account,</hi> do not belong only to Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and Preachers; for it extends to all the People alſo, for it ſhould be a conſtant Rule which they ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways bear in mind, and have recourſe unto in whatever they take in hand, or in whatever their hands finds them to do, <hi>To do it as ye that muſt give account.</hi> And becauſe this Judgment of God will reach to Thoughts and Words alſo; therefore the ſame Rule ſhould be expreſt yet a little more comprehenſively on this wiſe, So <hi>think, ſpeak, and do as ye that muſt give accovnt,</hi> according to what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and commanded by the Spirit, <hi>So ſpeak ye, and ſo do, as they that muſt be judged by the Law of Liebrty.</hi> Jam. 2.12. As one ſaith, <hi>Remember the End,</hi> (that is the laſt end of Things) <hi>and thou ſhalt never do amiſs:</hi> So in thy Walking, keep the Judgment of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in thine eye, and thou ſhalt never go much aſtray. We know
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153617:7"/>and are aſſured of it beforehand, That when the Great Day of his Judgment is come we may have no Excuſe or Plea; that of this and of every day of our Life, after we are come to the years of Diſcretion, and to the Knowledge of Good and Evil, we are not only in danger, but we ſhall certainly be called to an account.</p>
            <p>There is hardly any thing which is a greater Awe and Check to ſin, than a lively Faith of this future Judgment, to have it continually before our eyes, and to have our Thoughts and Apprehenſions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways upon it. <hi>Jerom</hi> an antient Servant of the Lord did ſay of himſelf, <hi>Whither I ſleep or wake, or whatever I do; Methinks I hear that voice always ſounding in my Ears, Ariſe ye dead, and come forth to judgment. And truly if we did with the eye of Faith, and with the eyes of our underſtanding being enlighmed, Behold till the Thrones were caſt down, and the antient of days did ſit, whoſe Garment was white as Snow, and the Hair of his Head like the pure Wooll; his Throne was like the fiery ſtream, and his wheels, as burning fire; A fiery ſtream iſſued and came forth from before him. Thouſand thouſands miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtood before him: The judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſet, and the Books were opened.</hi> Dan. 7.9, 10. Such a viſion the Prophet then had; and alſo <hi>John,</hi> when he <hi>ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great ſtand before God, and the Books were opened, and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life; and the Dead were judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of thoſe things which are written in the Books according to their works. And the Sea gave up the Dead which were in it, and Death and Hell delivered up the Dead which were in them, and they were judged every Man according to their works.</hi> Rev. 20.12, 13. Did we in the midſt of Life ſee thoſe things which we ſhall ſee when we are let forth into the Chambers of Death: but yet more eſpecially, as we ſhall ſee when the Great day of his Judgment is come, this would influence our whole Life and Converſation into the greateſt Awe and Seriouſneſs, fear and trembling, and watchfulneſs that can be. If even a Sinner and an ungodly Man were to riſe from the Dead, and live over his paſt Life again, he would be another kind of Man, and even he would be perſwaded unto God and good Things. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be a more forcible conſideration to make us to pleaſe God this little mean while, and to endeavour to the utmoſt to be reconciled unto him; then the knowledge how that we muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come unto and appear before him: It is the very ſame as to the compreheuſiveneſs and extenſiveneſs of the future Judgment: For then <hi>God is Judge himſelf Selah.</hi> Pſal. 50.6. <hi>And he hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a day in the which he will judge the World in righteouſneſs, by that Man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given Aſſnrance unto all Men, in that he hath raiſed him from the Dead.</hi> Acts 17.31. When the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſes his Belief of the Reſurrection of both the juſt and unjuſt; He thereupon immediately adds, <hi>Herein do I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153617:7"/>my ſelf to have a Conſcience void of offence towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Man.</hi> As Attorneys and Solicitors are now very diligent and induſtrious to get their Buſineſs, Witneſſes and Evidence all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the day of Aſſize or <hi>Niſi prius:</hi> So we ſhould prepare and make all things ready againſt that Day we ſhall be judged, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by whom it muſt be. And ſo to learn to behave and comport our ſelves, that we may <hi>not be condemned when we ſhall be judged.</hi> Pſal. 37.33. <hi>Others we read of, who will be condemned when th y ſhall be judged.</hi> Pſal. 109.7. It may be we have no Buſineſs at thoſe Aſſizes which are holden twice a year, but at this general <hi>Grave delivery,</hi> which is kept once for all our dead Bodies ſhall ariſe, and <hi>every one of us ſhall give account of himſelf to God.</hi> Rom. 14.12. What a comfort will it then be, as the ſame ſhould be our care now, to ſee well to it that our ſelves be acquitted out of that word whereby we ſhall be judged at the laſt Day: And where we ſee our ſelves acquitted and cleared out of that ſame World, there to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep ſo; keeping your ſelves in the love of God. It is beſt not to defile our Garments at firſt, which I gather from what is written. <hi>Thou hast a few names even in</hi> Sardis, <hi>which have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed their Garments, and they ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy.</hi> Rev. 3.4. But if they have been defiled by additional Sin and Tranſgreſſion, then what <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul</hi> writes unto the Chriſtians of his Time, is here proper and applicable. <hi>And ſuch were ſome of ye, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> 1 Cor. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. That is, ye are to get your Garments waſhed in the Blood of Jeſus, and in the ſprinkling of the Spirit; and when they are <hi>waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made clean.</hi> Iſa. 1.16. by the Word which proceeds forth through them, there be ſure to keep them clean, We ſhould copy out and follow the Example of Jeſus Chriſt as near as ever we can. Who went about doing good <hi>and ſuffered for us, leaving us an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that we ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi> Herein is our <hi>love made perfect, that we may have boldneſs in the day of Judgment, becauſe as he is ſo are we in this World.</hi> 1 John 4.17. And ſo when as to all thoſe Characters which we find recorded of him, we can find ſomewhat thereof in our ſelves even of him that was <hi>holy, harmleſs, undefiled, ſeparated from ſinners.</hi> And ſo we read of the <hi>meekneſs and gentleneſs of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> See well to it that all theſe and the like Qualities and Diſpoſitions be wrought, inlaid and formed within thee. And ſo thoſe fruits of the Spirit reckoned up in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23. <hi>Love, joy, peace, long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance.</hi> And beſides this, <hi>giving all diligence, add to your Faith virtue, and to Virtue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to Knowledge temperance, and to Temperance patience, and to Patience godlineſs, and to Godlineſs Brotherly kindneſs, Charity. 2 Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.5, 6, 7.</hi> For theſe alſo are Graces, Gifts and Fruits of the Spinte
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153617:8"/>and if we have theſe, this is the earneſt of the Spirit, that we are indeed ſealed unto the day of Redemption. <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his.</hi> So it follows likewiſe by the ſame conſequence, that if a Man have the Spirit of Chriſh, then he is Chriſt's; and belongs to him, and is one of his Members; So that not only where he is, there ſhall his Servant be. But where the Head is, there of neceſſity muſt be the Members, becauſe it is not whole and compleat without the Members. The Scripture doth often make uſe of this Compariſon. How the people of God are one Body, and Chriſt is their Head. The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks of a Roll of a Book. <hi>And he ſpread it before me, and it was written within and without; and there was written therein Lamentation, and Mourning, and Wo.</hi> Ezek. 2.9. So ſhould this ſame Bible (the Book of the Lord, both as it comprehends the old and New Teſtament) be to each of us written within and without. Written within, that isi written in our hearts, and engraven in our inward Parts; when we can turn inwards, and ſee how it is written there, as well as look what is written without in Ink and Paper. And whereas <hi>Ezekiel</hi> goes on to add, <hi>Therein was written lamentation, and mourning, and wo.</hi> This is too true as to all the Children of Diſobedience, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, Hypocrites, Sinners. Wicked, Ungodly, and ſuch like. But to the <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>obedient,</hi> to thoſe who have begun or are perfecting the good work, the ſame word ſpeaks comfort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, and bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>Some have called it <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> to ſpeak of the <hi>Light within,</hi> the <hi>Spirit within,</hi> the <hi>Word within.</hi> But in this thing, thoſe that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> have certainly ſpoken the thing that is right; for as it is noted of the falſe Prophets, <hi>They have not what ſhould confirm the Word;</hi> but as an evidence that they are true and right in this Thing (I would to God they were ſo in all others) we have the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures expreſly ſpeaking the ſame. <hi>After thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts and write it in their Hearts.</hi> Jer. 31.33. <hi>Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean from all your filthineſs, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you.</hi> (But this that follows is to our preſent purpoſe) <hi>A new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony Heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh, and I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes, and ye ſhall keep my Judgments and do them.</hi> Ezek. 30.25, 26, 27. <hi>That was the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World.</hi> Joh. 1.4. which it doth in his inward parts or within him. <hi>Neither ſhall they ſay, Lo here, or lo there; for behold the Kingdom of God is within you.</hi> Luke 17.21. <hi>The Word is very nigh unto thee, even in thy month and in thy heart.</hi> Deat. 30.14. Rom. 10.8. Indeed all true Religion is an inward Thing, and an inward
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153617:8"/>Work; for outward Acts of Worſhip or Bodily Exerciſe are but the Huſk or Shell: for as the Soul is within the Body, ſo the ſubſtance or vital parts of Religion, which is to the ſaving of the Soul, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inviſible alſo. Where any one or any ſort of People ſpeak according to the Scriptures of Truth, there Truth from whence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſpring up is to be received and embraced. But if it ſpeaks not according to the Word there it is to be rejected and not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, according to that ſpiritual Wiſdom and Divine method of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the Precious from the Vile, and gathering the good Fiſhes into Veſſels, and caſting the bad away.</p>
            <p>When we ſee our ſelves already acquitted and cleared out of that Word whereby we muſt be judged at the laſt Day, this muſt be a mighty Comfort and Aſſurance. And that ſame Word having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and annexed <hi>a Crown of Life unto Faithfulneſs to the Death.</hi> Rev. 2.10. <hi>Therefore my beloved Brethren, Be ye stedfaſt, unmovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, always abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know that your Labour is not in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58. From all this put together will appear the Neceſſity of Perſevering and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in the work of the Lord, in order to have a well grounded hope, evidence and aſſurance, Right and Title to have this Crown of Life, and to have our Labour in the Lord recompenced: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as himſelf hath promiſed, <hi>For thy works ſhall be rewarded,</hi> ſaith the Lord. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.16. There is no Point in Divinity more clear and certain, and of more undoubted Truth than the neceſſity of Perſeverance, in order unto Salvation. As alſo nothing is more put in mind of, repeated, and inculcated over and over in common Preaching, for the abundant care and ſafety of Souls. The ſame is alſo underſtood by common People, whether learned o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unlearned, He that knows any thing of God and Religion, knows this alſo, That if we would be ſaved, it is neceſſary in order thereto, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unto our Lives end in the Worſhip and Service of God, in doing his Will, and finiſhing his Work: For He and he only that endures unto the End, ſhall be ſaved. Whoſoever once puts his hand to this Plow and looks back, he is not worthy of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. In thoſe Scriptures which are given to make wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation, there are abundance of Truths and Affirmations to this purpoſe; ſo that there is no need to cite or rehearſe any more. But yet there are ſeveral people, who are for ſerving God for a ſpurt and for a ſeaſon, and they come to the Place of Hearing his Word for once and away. I have told ye often this will not do, A fit of Holineſs for a ſeaſon will not bring any one to Heaven. But God who cannot lye, hath promiſed to them who by <hi>patient continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in well doing ſeek for Glory, Honour, and Immortality. Eternal Life.</hi> Rom. 2.7. <hi>Without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> But that is ſuch holineſs as is ingrafted, fixed, conſtant and univerſal.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153617:9"/>The Souldiers of the antient Roman Empire, according to the Laws and Conſtitutions thereof, were diſbanded and diſmiſſed from any further Service in the Military Employment after the fiftieth Year. But the Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt are never diſbanded or diſmiſſed from his Service; and if any ſhould deſert, diſmiſs or diſband them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from his Service, they loſe their Crown, and they become liable unto puniſhment. We read of <hi>Mnaſon</hi> an old Diſciple, and <hi>thoſe that be planted in the Houſe of the Lord ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God, they ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in old Age; they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing.</hi> Pſal. 92.13, 14. As long as any of us have the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Good and Evil remaining with us, we are to do the Good and eſchew the Evil. As long as any one hath all his ſenſes left, (as there is none who lives out all his five ſenſes) to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil, he is to do the firſt and leave the laſt undone, according as he hath Power of Action. The Soul thinks as long as ever it is in the Body, and as long as one thinks his thoughts are to be bent and lifted up towards God, and Goodneſs, and Truth, and not to admit of, but caſt out all ſuch Evil and Vanity, which would lodge or lurk there. And this it ſignified and required by that great and Indiſpenſable command. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord with all thy heart and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy ſtrength, and with all thy mind. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me, Bleſs his holy name.</hi> Pſal. 103.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. So by all that is within us, and to our very utmoſt, God is to be ſerved and obeyed, and alſo to the utmoſt Period and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of time. As our Souls in their creation and making have a beginning in time, but they are without end of days, they being Properly Immortal. Even ſuch an obedience and ſervice doth the Lord our Creator require of us, which did and doth once begin and never end, until our ſervice here is crowned and conſummated with Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>What remains? But that ye who ſhall hear or read this, be in the viſions of God, as <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was, to ſee the dead ſmall and great ſtand before God, and ſeeing that they were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books according to their Works, therefore in every thing, ſo think ſpeak, and do as ye that muſt give Account. The word of Inſtruction which ariſes hence is this, that each of us ſeverally do order our Life and Converſation in this ſhort Time and mean while as near as ever we can according to all the words which are Written in thoſe Books, which are the Books of Scripture, and the Book of Conſcience. That is, to live up and according to all thoſe Thoughts of Good and Truth, which Conſcience doth ſuggeſt unto Man.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
